欢迎回来, 在这个视频中我们将会看到另一个很酷的例子
Welcome back, In this video we're going to look at another example of cool
这一次, 让我们超越简单的hello world的例子
programing. This time let's move beyond the simple hello world kind of examples
还有更令人兴奋的, 比如说, 最流行的阶乘函数,
and on to something more exciting, say, the ever popular factorial function. So,
为了写阶乘, 我们需要打开一个文件, 我们可以写一些代码。
in order to write factorial, we'll need to open a file, which we can write some code.
让我开始吧, 回想一下上节课每个很酷的程序都必须有一个
Let me start that. And recall from last time that every cool program has to have a
主类和主类被要求有一个主方法, 我们不关心
main class and the main class is required to have a main method. And we don't care
主方法返回的是什么, 所以我们只要它返回一个类型对象,
what the main method return, so we'll just have it return something a type object,
然后我们在文件中填上一个骨架, 现在我们准备好了
and then we'll just fill in a skeleton here on the file. And, so now we're ready
要写一些代码, 那么我们要用主方法做什么呢？
to write some codes. So what are we going to have the main method do? Well, before
实际上, 我们可以把它写出来, 在我们讲这个程序的核心之前,
we can actually write factorially, before we can get to the guts of this program,
这其实不是很困难, 我们需要再讨论一下IO, 因为
which is actually not very difficult. We need to talk about IO some more. Because
我们需要能够, 读写, 数字, 我们需要能够
we're going to need to be able to, read and write, numbers. We need to be able to
读取运行程序的用户的数字, 然后将其打印出来
read numbers from, the, the user who's running the program, and print them back
我们来复习一下关于IO的内容, 为了调用IO
out. So let's just review little bit about IO, also. In order to invoke the IO
函数, 我们需要一个IO对象, 其中一个IO函数是
functions, we need an IO object. And one of the IO functions is something that
打印出一个字符串, 让我们写一个我们已经知道怎么做的程序,
prints out a string. So let's just, write a program that we already know how to do,
只是为了确认我们记得这个, 并且, 我们可以编译这个程序, 它
just to confirm that we remember that. And, we can compile this program. And it
应该只打印一个, 我们看看, 确实是这样的, 所以它打印出了
should just print one. And, let's see. Indeed it does. Okay? So it prints out the
第一, 现在, 让我们回到这里, 让我们讨论如何做输入。
number one. And so now, let's come back here and let's talk about how to do input.
所以, 我们不只是打印出数字1, 而是打印出一个
So, instead of just printing out the number one, let's print out a strain that
用户输入, 在这里, 在这里, 我们要读取一个应变, 按顺序
the user types in. So, ins-, in here, we're going to read a strain. And in order
要做到这一点, 我们需要一个IO对象, 因为有另一个函数, 另一个方法,
to do that, we need an IO object because there is another function, another method,
叫做内应变, 好的, 这将会更新这个字符串, 并返回到字符串。
called in-strain. Okay. And so this will renew this string. And return to string.
为了确保我们得到了漂亮的输出我们把它连接到那个字符串
And to make sure that we get the nice output let's concatenate on to that string
一条新线, 这是。当它打印出这个字符串时它会是
a new line. So, this is just to. When it prints this string back out it will be
印在我自己的线上, 所以, 让我们试着编译这个, 牛排, 它编译,
printed on i ts own line. So, let's try compiling this, And steak. It compiles,
现在我们可以运行自旋, 记住UNIX中的bang命令运行前面的命令
And now we can run spin. Remember the bang command in UNIX runs the previous command
这是由相同的字母开始的, 现在程序运行, 它在等待, 因为它是
that began with the same letters. And now the program runs and it waits. Cause it's
等我输入一些东西, 如果我输入一个类型它会打印出一个
waiting for me to type something. And if I type it type in one it prints back one and
如果我输入42, 它会给我42, 现在我们要讲的下一件事
if I type in 42 it gives me back 42. And so now The next thing we need to talk
关于如何将字符串转换成整数, 因为如果我们要做a
about is how to convert strings into integers, because if we're going to do a
阶乘, 我们想要处理整数而不是字符串, 现在我们只是
factorial, we want to work on integers and not strings. And at the moment we're just
阅读和书写字符串, 所以, 有一个用酷写的库
reading and writing strings. So, there is a library written in cool that does
整数和字符串之间的转换, 我们将给出主类
conversion between integers and strings. And we're going to give the main class
这是该类的功能, 它被称为A2I, 用于ASCII到整数。
here the functionality of that class. Which is called A2I for ASCII to integer.
它定义了一堆方法, 可以在字符串和整数之间进行转换。
And that defines a bunch of methods, that can convert between strings and integers.
让我们在这里添加这些命令, 这是我们的字符串, 我们已经读过了
So let's add those, commands in here. So here, here's our string. That we've read
我们现在要做的是, 把它转换成整数, 让我
in. And what we want to do now is to, convert this into an integer. So let me
在这里加几个括号, 这是我们的字符串, 好吗？现在我们
just add a couple of parens here. So there's our string, okay? And now we're
要调用。在这个方法上, 抱歉, 我们要调用那个
going to invoke. On that the method I'm sorry we're going to call on that the
函数这个方法, A到i, 好吗？让我们再检查一下, 我们已经
function the method, A to I. Okay? And let's just double check here that we've
把朋友放在正确的地方, 这就是A2I的论点, 现在, 我们回忆一下
got friends in the right place. So that's the argument to A2I. Now, we recall that
当我们对一个方法进行调度时它就只是自己坐着不动
when we have a dispatch to a method and it's just sitting by itself with not
对象, 它被发送到self对象, self对象就是对象
object, it's dispatched to the self object. And the self object is the object
在当前的类中, 在本例中是主对象, 它有
of the current class that we're in. In this case the main object, which has
继承了A2I方法, 因此A2I函数应该在这里定义。
inherited the A2I methods, And so the A2I functions should be defined in there. Now
我们有一个整数, 如果我们愿意, 我们可以用这个整数做点什么。
we have an integer. And we can do something with that integer if we like.
那么, 让我们在这里添加一些听不清的内容假设我们只在其中添加了一个
So, let's add some more [inaudible] here and let's just say we add just one to the
整数, 好的, 一旦我们完成了整数, 不管它是什么运算
integer. Okay. And then once we're done with our integer. Whatever operation it is
我们要用整数来做我们需要把它转换成字符串
that we want to do with the integer we need to convert it back to a string so
我们可以把它打印出来, a有一个逆函数I2A可以这样做, 我
that we can print it out. An there's an inverse function I2A that will do. So, I
不知道在这一点上是否有所有的副本, 所以,
don't know if we have all the parens in the right places at this point. So,
我们来检查一下, 是的, 看起来应该是这样的, 这是, 读入a
let's just check. Yes. That looks like that should work. So this will, read in a
字符串, 转换, 把它转换成整数, 加1, 然后把它转换回一个字符串,
string, convert, convert it to an integer, add one to it convert it back to a string,
连接在一条新线上, 然后把它打印出来, 现在我们来看看是否所有这些
concatenate on a new line, and print it out. Now let's see if all that actually
工作, 让我们运行编译器, 这里有个问题, 它说我们有
works, so let's run the compiler and we have a problem here. It says that we have
一个未定义的类A, 原因是, 我们没有提供A2I的代码, 所以
an undefined class A to I. And the reason is, we didn't supply the code for A2I. So
如果我们看一下我们的目录, 我们会看到我已经在类文件中复制了
if we look in our directory here, we'll see I've already copied in the class file
对于A2I, 我鼓励你们去看那个代码, 它实际上是
for A2I. And I encourage you to go and look at that code. It's actually
有趣的代码, 可以看到转换是如何写得很酷的。
interesting code to see how the conversions are written in COOL.
但是现在我们需要讨论如何编译一个使用库的程序,
But now we need to talk about how to compile a program that uses a library, And
方法非常简单, 只需列出命令上的所有类文件
the way you do it is very simple. You just list all the class files on the command
当你调用编译器时, 它会把所有的内容都读出来, 然后把它们当作a
line when you call up the compiler. And it will read them all in and treat them as a
单个程序, 在这种情况下我们用A2I编译, 编译事实。
single program. So in this case we compile, compile fact together with A2I.
这是符合的, 然后我们可以运行它, 声音, 现在, 如果我输入3, 它
And that complies. And then we can run it. [sound]. And now, if I type in three, it
打印4, 如果我输入一个, 它会输出两个, 所以程序看起来是
prints four. And if I type in one, it prints two. And so the program seems to be
工作, 现在我们已经准备好写出我们的阶乘函数了
working. And now we're almost ready to write our factorial function. So what do
我们想要在阶乘中做什么呢？我们想要做的不仅仅是添加
we want to do in factorial? Well, we want to do something other than just adding
一个, 我们要调用, 我们的特殊函数factorial, 所以我们插入一个调用
one. Instead, we want to call, our special function factorial. So let's insert a call
到这里的阶乘, 好了, 我们消去+1, 然后我们来检查一下
to factorial in here. Okay, and let's get rid of the plus one. And then let's check
我们有需要的所有参数, 所以我们需要关闭A2I调用,
that we have all the parens that we need. So we need to close off the, the A2I call,
阶乘调用, I2A调用, 最后一个应该是out字符串
the factorial call, The I2A call. And then that last one should be the out string
调用, 它是, 好的, 现在我们可以给这个类添加一个方法事实, 事实是
call, And it is, Okay. So now we can add a method fact to this class, And fact is
我们需要一个整数参数, 所以我们需要一个参数, 它的类型是
gonna take an integer argument. So we need a parameter here, And it's type is in
力, 整个东西会返回一个整数, 然后是我们的主体
force. And the whole thing is gonna return an integer. And then we have body of our
功能, 可能是一个好主意, 只是为了确保我们得到了这么多
function, And probably a good idea here, just to make sure that we got this much
对, 做一些简单的事情, 让我们试着做一个返回的函数
right, to do something simple. So let's just try to make a function that returns
还有一个比它的参数, 所以这和我们之前做的是一样的
one more than it's argument. So this will do exactly the same thing that we had
在此之前, 我们先确认一下, 这是可行的, 用A2I进行新的编译
before and let's just confirm that, that is working. So EW compile with the A2I
现在我们有了一个语法错误, 我们看到我忘记了关闭
library and now we have a syntax error. And we see that I forgot the closing
这个方法的分号, 记住, 类体是一个方法列表,
semicolon here for the method. Remember the, the, class body is a list of methods,
并且每个方法都被分号终止, 必须再次尝试编译。
and each method is terminated by a semicolon, Must try compiling that again.
现在它编译, 我们运行它, 我们键入4, 给出一个规范5, 好的, 看起来
Now it compiles. Let's run it. We type in four gives a spec five. Alright, So looks
好了, 我们现在已经准备好了对factorial的代码进行正确的处理, 这将会
right we're ready now to actually right the code for factorial. And this is gonna
是反高潮的因为这是一个非常简单的代码如果我们写下来
be anti climactic because it's actually a very simple code if we write it
递归地, 我们来做一下, 这是怎么运作的呢, 大家都知道
recursively. So let's do that. So how's that going to work? Well, everybody knows
哈代希望的定义, 如果I等于0那么0的阶乘就是0
the definition by Hardy Hope. If I is equal to zero then the factorial of zero
是1, 我们有一个关键字, 然后一个, 否则阶乘就会变成
is one. And we have a keyword there then one, otherwise the factorial is going to
是I乘以, I减1的阶乘, 对, 如果是
be I times, the factorial of I minus one. Right, and then if statements in
听不清总是以关键字结尾, 所以这是一个if then
[inaudible] always end in the keyword [inaudible] so it's an if then else
听不清结构, 这实际上是整个定义, 现在我们
[inaudible] construct. And that is actually the entire definition. So now we
应该有一个实际计算阶乘的程序, 它会编译, 所以现在
should have a program that actually computes factorial, it compiles, so now
我们来运行一下, 3的阶乘是6, 而6的阶乘是720
let's run it. So factorial of three is six. And factorial of six, is 720 and that
看起来是对的, 如果我们再试一次用一个更大的数, 我们得到a, 我们
looks right. And if we try it one more time with a bigger number, we get a, we
得到一个很大的数字, 我们认为这可能是正确的, 不管怎样
get a large number, we think that's probably correct. And so, anyway our
阶乘函数, 是有效的, 现在让我们回到这里, 作为一个
factorial function, is working. So, now let's come back here, and just as an
练习, 让我们迭代地重写这段代码, 而不是使用a
exercise, let's rewrite this code iteratively. So instead of using a
递归函数, 让我们用一个循环来写, 为了听不清
recursive function, let's write it using a loop. And in order to that [inaudible]
要去掉这些代码, 我们需要什么呢, 我们需要
gonna get rid of that code. What are we going to need? Well, we're going to need
这里有一个累加器, 我们需要一个局部变量我们可以用它来做
an accumulator here. We're going to need a, a local variable that we can use to
积累阶乘计算的结果, 以及您声明本地的方式
accumulate the results of the factorial computation. And the way you declare local
听不清的变量是听不清的陈述, 或者是naudibl
variables in [inaudible] is with [inaudible] Statements, or naudibl
表达式, 我们把它叫做变量事实, 因为, 结果
expressions. So we're gonna have, let's call this, variable fact, for the, result
关于阶乘的, 注意这里我可以有一个同名的变量
of factorial. And notice here that I can have a variable that has the same name as
这个函数, 以及编程语言, 听不清
the function. And the programming language, [inaudible] will not get
对此感到困惑, 因为变量和函数, 扮演不同的角色, 所以我们会
confused about that, Because variables and functions, play different roles. So we'll
有阶乘的事实, 不好意思, 它是Int类型的, 我们把它初始化
have the factorial fact, excuse me, it's of type Int, and we do initialize it to
一个, 好了, 乘法会起作用, 我认为这是默认的
one. Alright, so that multiplication will work. I think that the default for
整数被初始化为0如果我们要这样做, 那就不太好了
integers is to be initialized to zero and that would not be good if we're going to
把事实和其他数字相乘, 好了, 那么, a
be multiplying up fact with other with other numbers. Alright, so then the, a let
它有两个部分, 它有你要声明的变量或变量。
has two parts. It has the variable or variables that you are declaring. This
实际上可以是一个变量列表, 我们这次只会有一个, 然后
could actually be a list of variables. We'll only have one this time. And then it
有一个主体, 这个表达式或者是一个事实变量的计算
has a body. The, the expression or the computation in which the fact variable is
有, 我们想做什么？我想我们需要把它设为a
available. And what do we want to do? So, I think we're gonna need to have this be a
语句块因为我们需要有不止一个语句
statement block 'cause we're gonna need to have more than one statement in the
序列, 我们马上就会知道为什么, 但是我们想要有一个循环。
sequence. And we'll see why in just a minute. But then we wanna have a loop. And
那么我们的循环会怎么做呢, 我们会说, 当我不等于
so what is our loop going to do? Well, we're gonna say while I is not equal to
0, 我们要做什么, 我们需要做什么来做循环体的开口
zero. What do we, and what do we need to do the opening for the loop body the
打开关键字被称为循环。声音。现在, 我认为我们将需要
opening keyword is called loop. [sound]. And now, I think we're going to need
另一个语句块, 让我们打开一个block, 我们可能需要
another statement block here. So let's open up a block. We're gonna probably need
要做不止一件事, 我们首先要做的是要有事实。
to do more than one thing. The first thing we want to do is we want to have fact. Be
事实乘以I, 所以我们知道我不是零所以我们需要将电流相乘
fact times I, so we know that I is not zero so we need to multiply the current
我的价值是积累结果然后我们想要减去1
value of I into fact to accumulate the result and then we want to subtract one
从我这里, 注意到, cool的赋值语句是这个反向箭头。
from I and notice that the assignment statement in cool is this backwards arrow.
这就是分配的方式, 也是初始化的方法,
That's how you do assignment. It's also how you do initialization. So,
初始化和赋值看起来是一样的, 然后我们可以关闭语句
initialization and assignment look the same. Then we can close off our statement
block, 好的, 所以while循环的主体始终是一个表达式。
block. Okay, so the body of a while loop is always a single expression. In this
这个表达式是由两个语句组成的块, 声音和
case, that expression is a block that consists of two statements. [sound] And
然后我们就可以结束循环了, 循环的结束是池的关键字。
then we can close the loop. And the closing for a loop is the pool key word.
然后现在我们在一个语句块中, 所以这个必须以分号结尾。
And then now we're in a statement block, so this has to end with a semicolon.
注意这里的语句块从let开始, 现在我们想要的结果是
Notice the statement block up there from the let, And now we want the result of the
让block或let表达式成为阶乘, 不管怎样, 不管我们是什么
let block, or the let expression, to be factorial. So whatever the, whatever we
从while循环中跳出来, 不管我们在while循环中计算出什么, 我们都想要
got out of the while loop, whatever we computed in the while loop, we want that
这是整个let表达式的结果, 这是最后一个
to be the result of the entire let expression. [sound] so that's the last
我们的博客的声明, 请记住声明博客的最后一句话, 是
statement of our blog. Remember the last statement of a statement blog, is the
博客的价值, led的主体是led的结果, 所以事实会
value of the blog. The body of the led is the, the result of the led, so fact will
这也是整个领导陈述的结果, 这仅仅是
also be result of the whole led statements, it's just the result of the
声明博客, 因为, 阶乘方法本身就是led
statement blog. And since the body of the, factorial method itself is just the led
表达式, 事实将会是整个事件的结果, 所以, 如果我们
expression, fact will be the result of the whole thing. And so this, if we've
写的, 没有犯任何错误, 应该是阶乘的迭代版本, 所以,
written, haven't made any mistakes, should be an iterative version of factorial. So,
让我们来编译这个, 令人惊讶的是, 它符合第一次尝试, 现在让我们
let's compile this. And amazingly it complies on the first try. And now let's
运行它, 声音和哇！它真的有用, 所以我们有6个, 我们来做一下
run it. [sound] And whoa! It actually works. So we got six. And let's just do
还有一个测试, 为了让我们相信, 事情是有效的
one more test, to see that, to convince ourselves that, things are working
很好, 它们是。现在, 让我指出, 一个, 常见的, 错误的
reasonably well, and they are. Now, let me just point out, one, common, mistake, that
你可以很容易地做出, 而且, 当我还没有为a写一些很酷的程序时
you can easily make, and, that I make when I haven't written cool programs for a
如果你是一个C或程序员或者Java程序员, 你可能会想
little while. If you're a C or programmer or a Java programmer, you might, think
写作业, 像这样, 所以我用等号来写
about, writing assignments, like this. So I just use the equal sign to write
作业, 如果你熟悉的话, 看起来很好
assignment. That looks completely fine if you're, if you're familiar with those
语言, 或者用于这些语言的编程, 现在, 让我们看看会发生什么
languages, or used to programming in those languages. And now, let's see what happens
当我们试着编译这个的时候, 哦, 它编译的很好, 然后发生了什么
when we try to compile this. Oh, it compiles just fine. And then what happens
当我们试图运行它时, 它运行, 听不清输入所以我们给它输入
when we try to run it. Well it runs [inaudible] input so let's give it input
然后, 我们看到热量耗尽了, 这看起来是无限的
and. Then we see that we've run out of heat. And that looks like an infinite
循环, 所以我们在循环中绕圈, 消耗内存是有原因的。
loop. So we're going around and around the loop And consuming memory for some reason.
我们会在课堂上笑得很晚, 为什么, 为什么这个循环
And we'll, we '[laugh] get to that much later in the class. Why, why this loop
实际上, 最终消耗了内存, 但是, 很明显, 我们没有足够的内存
actually ends up consuming memory. But, clearly, we don't have enough memory, in
这个循环, 最后我们用完了, 所以这是一个确定的信号
the loop, and, and eventually we run out. And so, so that's a sure sign Of an
无限的外观, 这里发生了什么？它等于, 等于, 等于
infinite look. So what is going on here? Well the thing is that equals. Equals
cool的运算符是比较运算符, 听不清我们比较了I
operator in cool is the comparison operators. [inaudible] Well we compared I
和O一起返回一个布利, 这些都是非常有效的
with O and that returns a boullion. So these are perfectly valid cool
表达式, 它们刚好是布利子, 所以, 你从来没有
expressions. They just happen to be boullions. So, you don't ever actually I
或者是这个程序中的阶乘, 你只是比较了事实和事实
or factorial in this program. Your just comparing fact with factoid body and I
用i-1, 程序很乐意这么做, 它只是
with I minus one and the program is perfectly happy to do that. It just
不计算阶乘函数, 它永远不会终止, 因为我从来没有
doesn't compute the factorial function. And it never terminates, because I never
达到0, 这就结束了我们的阶乘例子, 我们再做一个
reaches zero. So that concludes our factorial example. And we'll do one more
再举个例子, 一个更复杂的, 一个很酷的程序
example next time of a more complicated, of a, of a cool program with some
非平凡的数据结构。
non-trivial data structures.